A Guide to the Records of the Arlington County Democratic Committee, 1952-1978
Arlington Public Library, Center for Local History
Arlington Public Library, Center for Local History
Records of the Arlington County Democratic Committee, 1952-1978
Arlington Public Library, Center for Local History
RG 137
12 boxes.
Arlington County Democratic Committee
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
The collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
Donated by the Arlington County Democratic Committee in 2002.
Scope and Content
Record Group 137 houses the records of the Arlington County Democratic Committee. The record group measures approximately 5.5 linear feet and dates from 1952 to 1978, with the majority of the materials dating from the 1960s. Types of materials include minutes, campaign flyers, sample ballots, delegate forms for local and state political conventions, precinct poll books, financial records, and clippings.
The Arlington Democratic committee has as its function the promotion of the objectives and platform of the Democratic Party. Series 1, Subseries 1 concerns Arlington and Virginia conventions, chiefly for 1964. Subseries 2 contains internal party papers including voter lists and election returns, political surveys, minutes, and correspondence. Series 2 contains local and state, with some national campaign flyers and promotional materials, chiefly for the 1960s with some from the 1950s and 1970s. Series 3 contains clippings removed from the other series.
The records document the changing attitudes of the Arlington Democrats throughout the 1950s and 1960s, as well as concerns about race relations, poll taxes, education, city growth, voting irregularities and Hatch Act compliance. Clippings, correspondence, and minutes show tensions between the conservative and liberal wings of the party, especially during the 1964 campaign, when conservatives were not enthusiastic about the national ticket.
A few representative names appearing in the records are: William Graham, chairman of the committee in 1964; Ralph Kaul, the 1960 candidate from the 10th District; Augustus C. (Gus) Johnson, the 1964 candidate for Congress from the 10th Virginia District; Joel T. Broyhill, longtime Republican congressman for the 10th District; and Mary A. Marshall, long serving delegate in the Virginia House.
Arrangement
Record Group 137 is organized into three series. Series 1, Subseries 1 is arranged chronologically, and Subseries 2 alphabetically. Series 2 and Series 3 are arranged chronologically.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Related Material
Researchers interested in Arlington and Virginia politics may consult a variety of record groups, including for example Record Group 65, Personal Papers of Mary A. Marshall; Record Group 94, Arlingtonians for a Better County; and Record Group 19, Personal Papers of Elizabeth Pfohl Campbell, an Arlington School Board member and activist.
Index Terms
Subjects:
Arlington County (Va.) -- Politics and government.; Virginia -- Politics and government; Political parties -- Unites States.; Democratic Party (U.S.); Democratic Party (Va.); Arlington County (Va.); Arlington (Va.)
Contents List
- Arlington Democratic Committee Convention and Internal Affairs
  - Arlington and State Conventions
    - Democratic Convention Delegate Ballot, 1956 (Box 1)
    - Resolution Calling for the Arlington County Democratic Convention, 1956 (Box 1)
    - Arlington County Democratic Convention Rules of Order, 1956 (Box 1)
    - Arlington County Democratic Convention Credentials, 1956 (Box 1)
    - Arlington County Democratic Convention Slate Ballot, 1956 (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous Papers re: 1956 Virginia State Democratic Convention, 1956 (Box 1)
    - Resolution Calling for the Arlington County Democratic Convention, 1964 (Box 1)
    - Arlington County Democratic Convention Minutes, Rules of Order, and Resolutions, 1964 (Box 1)
    - Arlington County Democratic Convention Committees, 1964 (Box 1)
    - Arlington County Democratic Convention Delegate Declarations, 1964 (Box 1)
    - Arlington County Democratic Convention Precinct Lists, 1964 (Box 1)
    - Arlington County Democratic Convention Financial Papers, May-June 1964 (Box 1)
    - Arlington County Democratic Convention Delegate Legality Correspondence, 1964 (Box 1)
    - Slate of the Committee for Good Democratic Government Nominated by William Graham, 1964 (Box 1)
    - Arlington County Democratic Convention Ballots, 1964 (Box 1)
    - Arlington County Democratic Convention Proxies, May 28, 1964 (Box 1)
    - Resolutions Concerning State Democratic Convention, 1964 (Box 1)
    - Steering Committee Report from Arlington Delegation to State Convention, 1964 (Box 1)
    - Lists of Arlington Democratic Delegates to State Convention, 1964 (Box 1)
    - Democratic Delegates Caucus Minutes, 1964 (Box 1)
    - Memo to Delegates to State Convention, June 7, 1964 (Box 1)
    - Room Reservation Request Forms for State Convention (Box 1)
    - Arlington County Democratic State Convention Delegate Declarations, 1964 (Box 1)
    - Correspondence re: Arlington and State Democratic Conventions, 1964 (Box 1)
    - Arlington Delegation Proxies for State Democratic Convention, June-July 1964 (Box 1)
    - Arlington Delegation Alternate Appointment Forms for State Convention, June-July 1964 (Box 1)
    - State Democratic Convention Programs and Badges, 1964 (Box 1)
    - Arlington County Democratic Convention Materials, 1970 (Box 1)
  - Committee Affairs
    - Action Course in Practical Politics (Box 2)
    - Application for Ballot (Box 2)
    - Assorted LIsts, n.d., 1962-1964 (Box 2)
    - Assorted Lists, 1965 (Box 2)
    - Assorted Lists, 1966-1975 (Box 2)
    - Arlington Democratic Committee Bylaws, 1962-1965 (Box 2)
    - Campaign Technique Brochures, 1950s-1960s (Box 2)
    - Caucus: Agreements, Memoranda, correspondence, 1961-1967 (Box 2)
    - Chairman's Report, 1961-1963 (Box 2)
    - Committee Correspondence, 1961-1962 (Box 2)
    - Committee Correspondence, 1963 (Box 2)
    - Committee Correspondence, 1964-1966 (Box 2)
    - Committee Correspondence, 1967-1970 (Box 2)
    - Doctors for Broyhill Correspondence, 1963 (Box 2)
    - Committee Election Materials, 1960-1961 (Box 3)
    - Committee Election Materials, 1963-1969 (Box 3)
    - Election Returns, 1957-1961 (Box 3)
    - Election Irregularities, 1964 (Box 3)
    - Financial Statements, 1965-1967 (Box 3)
    - Hatch Act Lawsuit in Maryland: Legal Papers, Correspondence, 1965 (Box 3)
    - Jefferson Jackson Day Dinners: Brochures, Correspondence, Lists, 1964-1967 (Box 3)
    - Lists Used in School Board Race, 1970-1972 (Box 4)
    - Lists Used in School Board Race: Directory of Teachers and Administrators (Box 4)
    - Lusk Reports, 1961 (Box 4)
    - Lyon Village Poll List (Box 4)
    - Madison Precinct Poll Books, 1961-1963 (Box 4)
    - Marshall Precinct Poll Books, 1954, 1956, 19611965, 1967 (Box 4)
    - Marchal Precinct Voters Lists, 1968 (Box 4)
    - Mass Meeting Papers, 1972 (Box 4)
    - Minutes, Agendas, 1961, 1962, 1967 (Box 4)
    - Report re: Non-Partisans in Arlington (Box 4)
    - Oak Ridge Poll Book, 1963 (Box 4)
    - Political Surveys: Fairfax County, 1965 (Box 4)
    - Political Surveys: Master Breakdown, 1966 (Box 4)
    - Political Surveys: Joseph Napolitan Association, 1966 (Box 5)
    - Political Surveys: Tenth Congressional District, 1962 (Box 5)
    - Political Surveys: Tenth Congressional District, 1966 (Box 5)
    - Poll Tax Repeal: Correspondence, Petitions, 1963 (Box 5)
    - Precinct Revision Reports, 1961-1962 (Box 5)
    - Precinct Worker Guides -- Democratic, 1962-1968 (Box 5)
    - Precinct Worker Guide -- Republican, 1962 (Box 5)
    - Primary Election of Committeemen Report, 1965 (Box 5)
    - Programs, 1966-1968 (Box 5)
    - Redistricting Materials, 1964 (Box 5)
    - Resolutions (Box 5)
    - Sample Ballots: Democratic, 1961-1976 (Box 5)
    - Sample Ballots: Republican and Independent, 1968-1976 (Box 5)
    - Street Directory Information (Box 5)
    - Transportation Research Forum Bylaws and Ballot, 1965 (Box 5)
    - Virginia State Democratic Materials, 1968 (Box 5)
    - Committee Vote Tally on Ricks-Fisher Recommendation (Box 5)
    - Voting Information (Box 5)
- Election Materials
  - Campaign Flyers, Guide for Canvassers, Voting Information, Democratic Party Plans, 1932, 1959 (Box 6)
  - Kaul for Congress Campaign Materials, 1960 (Box 6)
  - 1961 Campaign Correspondence, 1961 (Box 6)
  - Arlington Democratic Campaign Materials (General), 1962 (Box 6)
  - 1962 Campaign Correspondence, 1962 (Box 6)
  - 1962 Congressional Election: Joel Broyhill Flyers, 1962 (Box 6)
  - 1962 Congressional Election: Gus Johnson: Flyers, Sample Ballots, 1962 (Box 6)
  - 1962 Campaign Contribution Records, 1962 (Box 6)
  - Inaugural Anniversary Salute Materials, 1962 (Box 6)
  - Press Releases, Republican, 1962 (Box 6)
  - 1963 Election Democratic Flyers, Sample Ballot, Candidate Questionnaire, 1963 (Box 6)
  - 1963 Election Correspondence, 1963 (Box 6)
  - Press Releases, 1963 (Box 6)
  - 1963 Election Republican Flyers, Sample Ballot, 1964 (Box 6)
  - 1964 Congressional Election: Gus Johnson: Flyers, Sample Ballots, Report, 1964 (Box 6)
  - 1964 Presidential Campaign Flyers, Brochures, 1964 (Box 6)
  - Campaign Correspondence, 1964 (Box 6)
  - Press Releases, 1964 (Box 6)
  - 1965 Virginia Election: Correspondence, Press Releases, 1964-1965 (Box 7)
  - 1965 Virginia Election Campaign Materials, 1965 (Box 7)
  - 1966 Campaign Delegate and Field Worker Information, 1966 (Box 7)
  - 1966 Campaign and Primary Flyers, Sample Ballots, etc., 1966 (Box 7)
  - Correspondence re: 1966 Election, 1966 (Box 7)
  - 1967 Campaign Flyers, Sample Ballots, 1967 (Box 7)
  - 1967 Campaign Correspondence, Candidate Information, Precinct Information, 1967 (Box 7)
  - 1968 Campaign Flyers, Democratic, 1968 (Box 7)
  - 1968 Campaign Flyers, Republican and Independent, 1968 (Box 7)
  - Joe Wholey Campaign Problem Research Report, 1968 (Box 8)
  - 1969 Campaign Flyers, Sample Ballots, Bumper Stickers, 1969 (1) (Box 8)
  - 1969 Campaign Flyers, Sample Ballots, Bumper Stickers, 1969 (2) (Box 8)
  - 1969 Campaign Correspondence, 1969 (Box 8)
  - Statement re: Interstate 66, 1970 (Box 8)
  - 1971 Election Brochures and Convention Tallies, 1971 (Box 8)
  - 1973 Campaign Flyers, 1973 (Box 8)
  - 1974 Campaign Flyers, 1974 (Box 8)
  - 1975 Campaign Flyers, 1975 (Box 8)
  - 1976 Campaign Flyers, 1976 (Box 8)
  - 1978 Campaign Flyers, 1978 (Box 8)
- Clippings
  - Clippings re: Virginia Politics, 1955-1960 (Box 9)
  - Campaign Clippings, 1961 (Box 9)
  - Clippings re: 1961 Virginia Election, 1961 (Box 9)
  - Election Returns Clippings, 1960-1962 (Box 9)
  - Campaign Clippings, 1962-1963 (Box 9)
  - Election Returns Clippings, 1963-1965 (Box 9)
  - Clippings re: Arlington Democratic Convention, 1964 (Box 9)
  - Clippings re: Democratic State Convention, 1964 (Box 9)
  - Campaign Clippings, 1964 (Box 9)
  - Clippings re: 1965 Virginia Election, 1965 (Box 9)
  - Campaign Clippings, 1966 (Box 10)
  - Election Returns Clippings, 1966-1969 (Box 10)
  - Campaign Clippings, 1967 (Box 10)
  - Clippings re: 1968 Election, 1968 (Box 10)
  - Clippings re: 1969 Election, 1969 (Box 10)
  - Clippings re: 1970 Election, 1970 (Box 10)
  - Election Returns Clippings, 1970 (Box 10)
  - Clippings re: 1971 Election, 1971 (Box 11)
  - Clippings re: Elections, 1972 (Box 11)
  - Election Returns Clippings, 1973 (Box 11)
  - Election Returns Clippings, 1975 (Box 11)
  - Election Returns Clippings, 1976 (Box 11)
- ARTIFACTS BOX 1
  - Fisher Ricks button from Series 4, Subseries 1, File 5
  - Yes We Need Pools button from Series 4, Subseries 3, File 5
  - Charles Wood Arlington County Board Button, from Series 4, Subseries 3, File 5